Beverly Cassara Papers
Beverly Cassara Papers
- Correspondence-subject files
  - University of the District of Columbia
    - Summer faculty research grant, 1987-1988; undated; includes report by BC (Box 27)
    - Yearbooks (FCC only), 1976; 1977; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - University of Nairobi
    - Awards and recognitions, 1981 (Oversize 3)
    - Correspondence, 1981; 1983-1987,; undated (Box 28)
      See also Karani, Florida; Kinyanjui, Peter.
    - Miscellanea, papers, reports, syllabi, newsletters; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - University of Southern Maine
    - Correspondence, 1989-1996; undated (Box 28)
      See also Callender, Willard; "Professors of Adult Education Survey on Racism and Diversity".
    - Course material, correspondence, syllabi, class schedules, reading lists, student lists and grades
      - HRD 631, The Adult Learner, 1991; 2 folders (Box 29)
      - HRD 646, Introduction to International Adult Education, 1988-1996; undated; 6 folders (Box 29)
      - HRD 646, Introduction to International Adult Education, 1988-1996; undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
      - International careers workshop, 1992; 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Printed material (Box 30)
  - University of the State of New York, State Education Department, 1983; 1985 (Box 30)
  - USSR/Finland trip
    - Audiorecordings, See Audiovisual material: Finnish Assoc. of Ad. Ed. and Audiovisual material: Minister of Education Finland
    - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 30)
    - Papers and notes, BC notes, photo, paper by Onoushkin, "Adult Education in the USSR: The State of the Art and Prospects for the Future," report by BC, "Adult Educators Visit the USSR and Finland" (Box 30)
      See also Personal papers: Journals: 1987 [USSR/Finland trip].
    - Slides, 1 carousel and 1 small box (Oversize 5)
    - Miscellaneous, receipts, souvenirs, memorabilia (Box 30)
  - Van Doren, Ruth, 1968; 1970,; 1976,; undated (Box 30)
  - Vermont Civil Rights Union, 1966 (Box 30)
  - Vermont Governor's Commission on the Status of Women, 1970; undated; BC was chairman of the Commission (Box 30)
  - Virginia Association of Adult and Continuing Education (VAACE), 1972; 1974,; 1986 (Box 30)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1971; 1974-1976,; 1984,; 1987; correspondence, site visit report on VPI's College of Education, proceedings of "Continuing education in action" conference (Box 30)
  - Wanjala, Chris, undated; manuscript of paper "Discovering East African Poets" (Box 30)
  - Washington Post, 1988 (Box 30)
  - Washington Women's Forum
    - Awards and recognitions, 1977; 1979 (Oversize 3)
    - Correspondence, 1979; 1980,; 1982,; 1983-1985 (Box 31)
  - Weinberg, Johannes, 1967 (Box 31)
  - Wersich, Rüdiger, 1982; 1985-1986,; 1988,; 1995-1997 (Box 31)
  - Wesseler, Matthias, 1980-1983; 1985,; undated; German participatory research scholar; correspondence, set of papers edited by Wesseler (Box 31)
    See Audiovisual material: German adult educators interviews: Wessler.
  - WETA
    - Awards and recognitions, 1983 (Oversize 3)
    - Interview with Cassara, See Audiovisual material: Women of Achievement Beverly Cassara interview.
    - Publicity and notes for BC's interview, 1983; 1986 (Box 31)
  - The White House, 1968; 1992,; 1997 (Box 31)
  - Who's Who and similar directories, publicity and biographical sketches for a number of 'who's who" type directories (Who's Who in the East, World Who's Who of American Women, etc), alphabetically by directory title (Box 31)
  - Women's Equity Action League (WEAL), 1975; 1977,; undated (Box 31)
  - World Affairs Council, 1995 (Box 31)
  - World Bank, 1995 (Box 31)
  - World Conference on Education for All, 1990; information packet; includes speech by Francesco Vio Grossi, president of ICAE (Box 31)
  - World Congress of Comparative Education (7th), 1989; conference material, proceedings, papers (edited by Alexander Charters and BC) (Box 31)
  - World Federalist Association, 1989; 1992,; undated (Box 31)
  - WRC-TV
    BC was inolved in several televised workshops and programs for WRC-TV over the years. This subseries includes correspondence, scripts, notes, viewer response letters, etc.
    - "A Woman Is...", 1973 (Box 31)
    - Educational and vocational guidance workshop for women, 1974 (Box 31)
    - "Man to Woman", 1977 (Box 31)
    - "HER-RAH!", 1978 (Box 31)
    - "Learning never ends", 1978 (Box 32)
    - BC notes and miscellany (Box 32)
  - YWCA, 1980; 1987-1989 (Box 32)
  - Zinn, Lorraine, See Philosophy of adult education inventory.
  - Miscellaneous
    - A-Z, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - A-Z, first names only or name unknown (Box 32)
- Writings
  - Articles, alphabetically by article title (Box 32)
  - Book proposals, proposal for American Men: Their Changing Roles (Box 32)
  - Book reviews, alphabetically by author of book being reviewed; includes reviews of books by Paolo Freire, William Griffith, and others (Box 32)
  - Books
    - Adult Education in a Multicultural Society
      Authors, in chapter order, are: Intro) Beverly Cassara, 1) Young Pai, 2) Charles Tesconi, 3) C. Ray Graham and Peter S. Cookson, 4) Charlotte Morgan, 5) John Tippeconnic III, 6) Martha Montero-Sieburth, 7) Don Nakanishi, 8) Philip and Vesta Daniel, 9) Thelma Barer-Stein, 10) Joan Reeves, 11) Kimerly Miller, Cornelius Grove and Bettina Hansel, 12) René Diaz-Lefebvre
      - Chapter abstracts (Box 32)
      - Contributor bios (Box 32)
      - Correspondence, See Correspondence-subject files: Adult Education in a Multicultural Society and individual authors.
      - Introduction and chapter drafts, drafts (Box 32)
      - Introduction and chapter drafts (cont.) (Box 33)
      - Introduction and chapter drafts (cont.) (Box 34)
      - Index (draft) (Box 34)
      - Typescript (Box 34)
      - Galleys (Box 34)
      - Published hardcover (Box 34)
      - Published paperback (Box 34)
      - Reviews, publicity and citations (Box 34)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 34)
    - Adult Education in a Multicultural Society electronic files, all are 5-1/4" floppy disks, file format unknown; titles are given exactly as written on diskette labels
      - CASSARA / BBC Book / Disk 1 / Backup, cassara_061; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / BBC Book / Disk 2 / Backup, cassara_062; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / BBC Book / Disk 3 / Backup, cassara_064; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / BBC Book / Disk 4 / Backup, cassara_065; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - Cassara / Substitute / 14CHAP7 / (Nakanishi) / - Backup -, cassara_063; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Book / Correspondence, cassara_067; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Title Page / Introduction / Acknowledgements / Biographies / Contents, cassara_068; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Instruct / Tesconi / Pai / 1, cassara_072; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Lefebvre / Sioburth [?] 2, cassara_070; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Morgan / Tippeconnic / 3, cassara_073; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Daniel / Borer-Stein / 5, cassara_074; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - CASSARA / Reeves / Miller / 4, cassara_071; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - Graham / Nakanishi / 6, cassara_069; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
      - Index-1 / >1<, cassara_066; Floppy disk: 5 1/4 inch (Oversize 4)
    - Adult Education Through World Collaboration, working title: Global Collaboration in World Education: Who's Doing What
      Authors, in chapter order, are: Preface) Beverly Cassara, Intro) Francisco Vio Grossi, 1) Paul Belanger, 2) John Holden and James Dorland, 3) Lawrence Cumming, 4) Paul Wangoola, 5) Jack McNie and Daniel Andreae, 6) Heribert Hinzen, 7) Ken Motoki and Yasumasa Hirasawa, 8) Gunnar Rydström, 9) Kees Epskamp, 10) John Comings, 11) Budd Hall, 12) Helena Kekkonen, 13) Darlene E. Clover, 14) Patricia Rodney, 15) Patricia Ellis, 16) Ana Maria Quiroz
      - Prospectus (Box 34)
      - Chapter abstracts, contributor bios (Box 34)
      - Correspondence, See Correspondence-subject files: Adult Education Through World Collaboration; Cosman, Bill; and individual authors
      - Preface, introduction and chapters (drafts), 18 folders (Box 35)
      - Index (draft) (Box 36)
      - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 36)
      - Galleys (Box 36)
      - Published hardcover (Box 36)
      - Reviews, publicity (Box 36)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 36)
    - American Women: The Changing Image
      - Drafts (Box 36)
      - Published hardcover (Box 36)
      - Reviews, publicity (Box 37)
        See also Speeches: [American Women: The Changing Image].
      - Japanese edition (Box 37)
  - Book chapters
    - Adult education in a multicultural society (in Erwachsenenbildung im Kontext), 1991; 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Developing curriculum with the culturally unique (in Materials and Methods in Continuing Education), 1975; 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Education for women as persons (in Encyclopedia on Women), circa 1978; note on first page says "encyclopedia was never published" (Box 37)
    - International studies in adult education (in Materials and Methods in Continuing Education), 1987 (Box 37)
    - Love and the affluent American housewife/mother (in The Future of Love and Loving) (Box 37)
    - Participatory modes (in Materials and Methods in Continuing Education), 1982 (Box 37)
    - Rethinking Adult Education for Development, 1993; collection of educators' responses to questionnaire; BC's responses are on p. 56. Other respondents include Lalage Bown, Alexander Charters, James Draper, Paolo Freire, Martha Friedenthal-Hesse, John Henschke, Roger Hiemstra, Cyril Houle, Peter Jarvis, Malcolm Knowles, Jost Reischmann, Kjell Rubenson, many more. (Box 38)
  - Dissertation: "A study of various kinds of educational growth of students in the Goddard College Adult Degree Program", 1970; readers/advisers were Malcolm Knowles, Eugene DuBois, Gene Phillips, and George Angell; 4 folders (Box 38)
  - Grant proposals (Box 38)
  - Journals, See Personal papers: Journals.
  - Papers
    - Access to opportunity in graduate education (Box 38)
    - Adult education at the University of Nairobi (Box 38)
    - Adult education in Kenya: a getting-acquainted study visit, 1982 (Box 38)
    - Adult educators visit the USSR and Finland, 1987 (Box 38)
    - American education policy presented through the example of vocational continuing education (Box 38)
    - Another place: a resource for continuing education for women (Box 38)
    - Are we admitting women to equal opportunity?, 1979-1980 (Box 38)
    - Career pathways, attitudes and aspirations of professional women in higher education institutions in West Berlin, Germany, circa 1976 (Box 38)
    - A concept for the establishment of an international development institute at the University of the District of Columbia (Box 38)
    - The development of an international component in an adult education graduate program, 1986 (Box 38)
    - Discussion of international research needs in the field of adult education, 1995 (Box 39)
    - Diversity by any other name, 1992-1994; co-authored with E. Michael Brady, Willard Callender, and Yizhong Zhou; this paper was also titled "Multiculturalism and diversity in adult education graduate school programs" and "Professors of adult education and the issue of diversity" and there is both a long version and a short version (Box 39)
      For the survey data on which this paper is based, see Correspondence-subject files: "Professors of Adult Education Survey on Racism and Diversity".
    - The education of low-income women: a participatory model (proposal), 1982 (Box 39)
    - Educational problems of mature women (course report) (Box 39)
    - The emerging role of women adult educators in Kenya, 1987; co-authored with Florida Karani, Lina Tungo Chesaro, Mary Kariuki, Prisca Muthoni, Mary Opiyo, and Agness Gichuru (Box 39)
    - Getting a university off the ground, 1979; published as a featured series in The Washington Post (Box 39)
    - History of the international component of the adult education graduate program at the University of the District of Columbia, 1990 (Box 39)
    - The how and why of preparing graduate students to carry out participatory researc h, 1987 (Box 39)
    - The influence of the liberal arts tradition on German adult education, circa 1982; paper, reviews; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Interculturalism and the responsibility of the adult educator, 1993 (Box 39)
    - International adult education and multicultural education: two sides of the same coin, 1986 (Box 39)
    - International aspects of graduate programs in adult education (Box 39)
    - International studies in adult education, undated; co-written with James Draper (Box 39)
    - Multiculturalism: the challenge to adult education in the United States, 1991 (Box 39)
    - Multiculturalism and diversity in adult education graduate school programs, See Diversity by any other name.
    - Observations of an American adult educator in Kenya, 1981 (Box 39)
    - Observations on the status of adult education in Germany today, 1981 (Box 39)
    - Opportunity remains unequal for women in academe, undated (Box 39)
    - Participatory modes for empowering the disadvantaged, 1987 (Box 39)
    - Participatory research: are adult education graduate programs ready for it?, 1989 (Box 39)
    - Participatory research for primary health care, 1988 (Box 39)
    - Participatory research: group self-directed learning for social transformation, 1986; 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Participatory research in the community: people doing it themselves, 1987 (Box 40)
    - Preparing graduate students to carry out participatory research, 1991 (Box 40)
    - Professional opportunities for women in adult education, circa 1970; includes photos (Box 40)
    - Reflections on international literacy year, 1990 (Box 40)
    - Reflections on my career as an international adult educator (Box 40)
    - The story of the Montana Housing Project Educational Center, 1975 (Box 40)
      BC wrote a number of articles, speeches, and papers on her experience with the Montana Housing Project. See for example Book chapters: Developing curricula with the culturally unique; Papers: Another place: a resource for continuing education for women; Siegen lectures: Needs assessment for the educationally underprivileged; Speeches: The concept of open learning and Speeches: The culturally unique: a wider focus on their educational needs
    - A survey of international adult education in degree-granting programs, 1982 (Box 40)
      For survey data on which this paper was based, see Research material: International studies in adult education.
    - Thoughts on the education of women in the United States in the 1990s (Gedanken zur Frauenbildung in den Vereinigten Staaten in den 90iger Jahren), 1991 (Box 40)
    - Traditional adult education in Kenya: some thoughts for today's world, 1990; co-authored with George Reche (Box 40)
    - Why study international education? (Box 40)
    - Women in development, 1990 (Box 40)
    - World collaboration for a global perspective, 1993 (Box 40)
    - Microfiche of papers in ERIC, abstracts of more than 20 papers by BC in ERIC, and microfiche versions of same (Box 40)
  - School papers, papers written for various graduate courses in adult and continuing education
    - Philosophy of education (Dan Marshall), 1954 (Box 40)
    - Social foundations of education (Peter Siegel), 1966 (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1951-1967; 2 folders (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 2 folders (Box 41)
  - Siegen lecture series
    In 1982, BC gave a series of lectures at the Universität Gesamthochschule Siegen in Germany. The material here includes both German and English versions and in many cases one or more drafts.
    - (1) Philosophies of adult education, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (2) Danish Volkshochschule movement, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (3) Antigonish, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (4) Highlander Folk School, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (5) Continuing education for mature women in the United States, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (6) Career patterns of female professors in West Berlin institutions of higher education, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (7) Participatory research, 1982 (Box 41)
    - (8) Needs assessment for the educationally underprivileged, 1982 (Box 42)
    - (9) Problems relating to literacy and development, 1982 (Box 42)
    - (10) Cooperative extension service in the United States, 1982 (Box 42)
    - (11) Adult education in Yugoslavia, 1982 (Box 42)
  - Speeches
    Speeches are in alphabetical order by title; titles assigned by the processor are indicated by square brackets
    - [adult education in Germany] (Box 42)
    - Adult education in the United States: an overview, 1976 (Box 42)
    - Adult education's response to the challenge of the women's movement, 1976 (Box 42)
    - [American women: the changing image], 1967 (Box 42)
    - Barre, VT speech, spring 1970 (Box 42)
    - [Burlington YWCA workshop for women], 1967; notes only (Box 42)
    - Cambridge women's group, Unitarian church, 1962 (Box 42)
    - Celebrating life, 1997; BC's remarks at Colby College 50th Class Reunion (Box 42)
    - The changing roles of men and women in marriage, 1967 (Box 42)
    - "College of Ed. UDC" (Box 42)
    - The concept of open learning: the case study of an adult education project in subsidised housing project in Washington, DC, 1976 (Box 42)
    - Counseling mature women (Box 42)
    - The culturally unique: a wider focus on their educational needs (Box 42)
    - Embracing the obvious: adult education goes international, 1990 (Box 42)
    - The environment: so many questions -- so few answers -- what to do?, 1992 (Box 42)
    - A few words about participatory research (Box 42)
    - "FIGS speech", circa 1996 (Box 42)
    - [international studies in adult education], circa 1985 (Box 42)
    - Non-traditional education in the United States, 1976 (Box 42)
    - [North Carolina Adult Education Association conference keynote address], 1978 (Box 42)
    - An overview of the sex-role question in the United States today, 1970 (Box 42)
    - Remarks made at a symposium in honor of the inauguration of Rafael L. Cortada as president of the University of the District of Columbia, 1988 (Box 42)
    - A report on the Highlander Folk School, 1970 (Box 42)
    - Senate hearing, 1972 or 1973; on H.R. 14643 (District of Columbia Postsecondary Education Reorganization Act) (Box 42)
    - U.N. speech material (Box 42)
    - [to University of the District of Columbia Board of Trustees] (Box 42)
    - U. of Wisconsin radio lecture (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Berlin, 1975-1976; notes from BC's Fulbright year, partial drafts of articles (Box 43)
    - Colby College class columns, 1993; undated; drafts of BC's alumni news columns for the Class of 1947 (Box 43)
    - Drafts of East German article, 1975-1976 (Box 43)
    - German language notes and translations (Box 43)
    - In the footsteps of Luther and Goethe: American tourists in East Germany, 1979 (Box 43)
    - Romantic old Heidelberg (Box 43)
    - Testimony for the hearing on regional research centers and laboratories (Box 43)
    - Unitarian Universalist Church, 1953; 1958,; 1967,; undated; readings, sermons, notes, miscellany (Box 43)
    - Notebook, spiral-bound notebook with miscellaneous notes (Box 43)
    - Miscellaneous, titled, non-adult-education articles, essays, drafts; alphabetical by title (Box 43)
    - Miscellaneous, untitled, non-adult-education articles, essays, drafts (Box 43)
    - Fragments (Box 43)
    - Author uncertain (Box 43)
- Research material
  - Antigonish movement
    - BC notes (Box 43)
    - Clippings (Box 43)
  - Folk schools - Highlander Folk School
    See also Correspondence-subject files: Highlander Research and Education Center.
    - BC notes (Box 43)
    - Clippings (Box 43)
    - Papers (Box 43)
    - Printed material (Box 43)
  - Folk schools - other, Sweden, Germany, Denmark
    - Audiorecordings, Per Himmelstrup, Danish Folk Adult Ed. Movement, See Audiovisual material: Danish Folk Adult Ed Movement - Per Himmelstrup (2 items)
    - Printed material, 2 folders (Box 44)
  - German adult educators
    - BC notes, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - BC notes (Box 45)
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
    - Clippings (Box 45)
    - Data, 3 folders (Box 45)
    - Findings and conclusions (Box 46)
    - Interviews, See Audiovisual material: German adult educators interviews (24 items)
    - Papers (Box 46)
    - Printed material, 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Printed material (Box 47)
  - Grundtvig
    - BC notes (Box 47)
    - Printed material and clippings, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - International studies in adult education
    - BC notes (Box 47)
    - Clippings (Oversize 1)
    - Papers (Box 47)
    - Printed material (Box 47)
    - Printed material (Box 48)
    - Surveys of adult education departments, 1978; 1986; 3 folders (Box 48)
    - Miscellany (Box 48)
  - Multicultural education
    - BC notes (Box 48)
    - Clippings (Box 48)
    - Clippings (oversize) (Oversize 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 48)
    - Papers (Box 49)
    - "Principles of multicultural education" course syllabus and reader (Box 49)
    - Printed material, 2 folders (Box 49)
  - Participatory research
    - BC notes (Box 50)
    - Clippings (Box 50)
    - Correspondence (Box 50)
    - Papers, 2 folders (Box 50)
    - Printed material, 3 folders (Box 50)
    - Printed material, 2 folders (Box 51)
  - Study circles
    - BC notes (Box 51)
    - Clippings (Box 51)
    - Correspondence (Box 51)
    - Printed material, 2 folders (Box 51)
    - Printed material (Box 52)
  - Women's issues
    - BC notes (Box 52)
    - Clippings (Box 52)
    - "Early 70s women's movement" [supplied title] (Box 52)
    - Papers (Box 52)
    - Printed material (Box 52)
    - Printed material (Box 53)
- Personal papers
  - Address books, undated; 3 folders (Box 53)
  - Appointment books and desk calendars, 1971-1990 (Box 53)
  - Appointment books and desk calendars, 1971-1990; 5 folders (Box 54)
  - Automobile papers, correspondence, advertising brochures, repair and service records and receipts (Box 54)
  - Awards and recognitions, awards, plaques, certificates of appreciation; foldered items are in alphabetical order by issuing organization (Box 55)
  - Clippings about, 1966-1970; 1975-1976,; 1978-1983,; 1985-1987,; 1989,; 1991,; 1995,; undated; 2 folders (Box 55)
  - "Correspondence record", list of colleagues, family members, and others with date contacted (Box 55)
  - Family memorabilia, children's artwork, birthday newspaper front page, dance recital program, etc. (Box 55)
  - Financial records, 1977; 1985,; 1989,; 1991 (Box 55)
  - Identity workshop notes, 1990; notes, class exercises, Myers-Briggs Type Inventory test (Box 55)
  - Journals
    - [fragments], 1966, Aug-Sep; few loose sheets of pink paper, photograph of one of BC's daughters (Box 55)
    - [fragments], 1970, April; few loose sheets of yellow legal paper (Box 55)
    - [BC's Fulbright year in Germany], 1975 (Box 55)
    - [BC's Fulbright year in Germany], 1975-1976 (Box 55)
    - [BC's Fulbright year in Germany], 1976 (Box 55)
    - [bound volume], 1976; includes 1 loose sheet (Box 55)
    - [fragments], 1977; few loose sheets (Box 56)
    - [bound volume], 1978; includes 1 loose sheet (Box 56)
    - [Germany], 1980; 3 softcover booklets (Box 56)
    - [Kemya trip], 1981; spiral notebook (Box 56)
    - [bound appointment book/desk calendar], 1982 (Box 56)
    - [bound appointment book/desk calendar], 1983 (Box 56)
    - [Kenya trip], 1985; spiral notebook (Box 56)
    - [USSR/Finland trip], 1987; loose sheets (Box 56)
    - [Hong Kong/Bangkok trip], 1990; loose sheets (Box 56)